Guide to the W.E.B. DuBois Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
W. E. B. Du Bois Collection
1889-1970
JWJ MSS 8
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2
(5 boxes)
The W. E. B. Du Bois Collection contains Correspondence, Writings, including drafts of Dusk of Dawn, and The World and Africa, and Subject Files.
Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The W. E. B. DuBois Collection contains items presented to the James Weldon Johnson Collection by Mr. DuBois, by way of Carl Van Vechten, with additional items from other persons.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
W. E. B. DUBOIS (1868-1963)
W. E. B. Dubois secured his position as one of the key voices in the argument over the role of the black man in modern America through his seemingly endless works of social activism. He was an educator (at Fisk University and Atlanta University), a founder of the Niagara Movement (which later merged into the NAACP), the long-time editor of the NAACP publication, The Crisis, a lecturer, political activist, and prolific writer. His works include: The Souls of Black Folk, Dusk of Dawn, and an Autobiography (published posthumously).
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials pertaining to W. E. B. Dubois.
African American authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963
- Correspondence, 1931; Series I
  - Bosley, Roberta, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    To: 1 / From: 0
  - Cook, Mercer, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cullen, Countee, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    To: 1 / From: 1 Includes letter from CC to Irene Diggs
  - Chicago Defender, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    To: 1 / From: 1
  - Gannett, Lewis, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Harcourt, Brace and Co. Inc., 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Johnson, James Weldon, 1931-38 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    To: 5 / From: 0
  - LaFarge, Oliver, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    To: 4 / From: 0
  - New York Herald Tribune, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    To the editor
    To: 0 / From: 1
  - [Nussbaum?], Anna, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Padmore, George, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Partington, Paul, 1961-70 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    To: 0 / from: 10
    Includes letters about DuBois research and photocopied issues of The Moon
  - Viking Press, 1946 Jun (Box 1, Folder 14)
    To: 0 / From: 2
  - Work, Monroe N., 1932 Jan (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Writings, Series II
  - "The Black Belt of Arkansas"
    - Article, typescript carbon, 7 p., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Colonies and Moral Responsibility"
    - Article, typescript carbon, 16 p., ca. 1948 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Abstracted from [ The World and Africa ]
  - Darkwater
    - Draft, typescript, corrected, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - Printed poem "Easter Emancipation, 1863-1913" with holograph revisions, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
      [became "Children of the Moon," pages 151-153 in previous draft]
    - Draft revisions, typescript carbon, corrected, incomplete, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
    - Draft, printed copy with holograph additions: chapter I, "The Shadow of Years", 1919 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Dusk of Dawn
    - Early draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
    - Later draft, typescript, corrected, incomplete, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
    - Later draft, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
    - Miscellaneous pages, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Review, 1940 Sep 7 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Ethiopia"
    - Article, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - The Gift of Black Folk
    - See also: The World and Africa
    - Draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34-38)
    - Miscellaneous notes and pages (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "Joseph Pulitzer"
    - Poem, typescript, 1911 Oct 30 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "Litany at Atlanta"
    - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - The Negro
    - Early draft pages with notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Draft chapters, typescript and carbon, corrected, 1914-15 (Box 2, Folder 43-51)
    - "Suggestions for Further Reading," typescript carbon (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Miscellaneous draft pages, typescript and holograph (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - "The Prayers of God"
    - Poem, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - "The New Negro Church"
    - Article, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - "A Pageant in Seven Decades"
    - Printed version, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - "The Renaissance of Ethics"
    - "a critical comparison of Scholastic and Modern Ethics" Thesis in Philosophy IV, holograph, 52 p., with notes and comments by William James, 1889 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - "Sacco and Vanzetti"
    - Outline and synopsis of play, holograph and typescript (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - The Souls of Black Folk
    - Fragment, numbered 307-310 (conclusion), holograph, corrected, ca. 1903 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - "The Superior Race"
    - Article, typescript carbon and proofs (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - "A Woman in Black"
      - Poem, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - The World and Africa
    - List of portraits proposed for book, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Circular letter enlisting aid of scholars, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - "A Book Note," drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Table of contents, drafts, holograph, typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Postscript, draft, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Outline of chapters I & II (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Book drafts
      - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 68)
        Includes: chapter IV, "Africa Rises from the Sea" chapter V, "The Peopling of Africa" chapter VI, "Egypt" chapter VI, "The Land of the Burnt Faces" chapter VII, "The Land of the Burnt Faces" chapter VIII, "Europe in Africa" chapter IX, "Atlantis"
      - Typescript, corrected, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 69)
        Includes: Foreword, Table of contents chapter I, "The Collapse of Europe" chapter II, "The White Masters of the World" "A History of the Gold Coast and Ashanti"
      - Typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 70)
        Includes: Forward chapter I, "The Collapse of Europe" chapter II, "The White Masters of the World" chapter III, "The Rape of Ethiopia" "A History of the Gold Coast and Ashanti"
    - Chapter drafts
      - "Africa Rises from the Sea", notes and parts of pages, typescript carbon, corrected (Box 3, Folder 71)
      - "Andromeda", two versions: typescript, corrected, and carbon (Box 3, Folder 72)
      - "Asia in Africa", two versions: typescript, corrected and typescript carbon (Box 3, Folder 73)
      - "Atlantis," two versions: typescript, corrected and typescript carbon (Box 3, Folder 74)
      - "The Black Sudan", three versions: Two typescripts, corrected and one typescript carbon (Box 3, Folder 75)
      - "Central Africa and the March of the Bantu," typescript carbon (Box 3, Folder 76)
      - "The Collapse of Europe," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 77)
      - "Congo and East Africa," typescript carbon (Box 3, Folder 78)
      - "Egypt," three versions: one typescript, corrected and two typescript carbons (Box 3, Folder 79)
      - "Egypt," notes and miscellaneous pages (Box 3, Folder 80)
      - "Europe in Africa," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 81)
      - "The Flight of the Bantu", two versions: typescript, corrected and typescript carbon (Box 4, Folder 82)
      - "The Land of Burnt Faces", two versions: typescript carbons and loose pages (Box 4, Folder 83)
      - "The Outpouring of Asia", two versions: typescript, corrected and typescript carbon (Box 4, Folder 84)
      - "The Peopling of Africa", four versions: two typescripts, corrected and 2 typescript carbons (Box 4, Folder 85)
      - "The Peopling of Africa," notes and miscellaneous pages (Box 4, Folder 86)
      - "The Rape of Ethiopia", four versions: two typescripts, corrected and two typescript carbons (Box 4, Folder 87-88)
      - "White Masters of the World", two versions: typescript, corrected and typescript carbon (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Notes and miscellaneous pages (Box 4, Folder 90-97)
    - Notes and miscellaneous pages (Box 5, Folder 98-101)
  - Untitled works
    - Fragment of article on Pan-Africanism Typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Fragment, article on education, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 103)
- Subject Files, 1916; Series III
  - Amenia Conference (1916) (Box 5, Folder 104)
    Includes: two programs and resolution signed by participants
  - Amenia Conference (1933) (Box 5, Folder 105)
    Includes: Memoranda, publicity statements, and findings
  - DuBois Literary Prize, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 106)
    Includes: Publicity statements and letters
  - Encyclopedia of the Negro, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 107)
    Includes: Memorandum, and carbons of letters
  - "International Integration of Negroid Peoples" by E. H. Steele, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 108)
    (Mimeograph with handwritten notes by EHS)
  - N.A.A.C.P., 1931-48, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 109)
    Includes: copies of memoranda from DuBois
  - United Nations, A Statement on the Denial of Human Rights to minorities in the case of Citizens of Negro Descent in the United States
    Edited by, with an introduction by WEBD
    - Mimeograph, with revisions, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Mimeograph, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - "A Summary of the Petition to the U.N.," draft, mimeograph, corrected and mimeograph copy, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - "Statement of Dr. W. E. B. DuBois to the Representatives of the Human Rights Commission.," typescript, signed with mimeograph copy, signed, and clipping, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 113)